Guide to the Medical Society of the County of Kings collection 1985.116
Brooklyn Historical Society
Medical Society of the County of Kings collection
1852-1981
Brooklyn Historical Society
Medical Society of the County of Kings (Kings County, N.Y.). Library
Medical Society of the County of Kings and Academy of Medicine of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Medical Society of the County of Kings (Kings County, N.Y.)
Medical Society of the County of Kings and Academy of Medicine of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Library
Williamsburgh Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Williamsburgh Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
Brooklyn Eastern District Dispensary and Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
1985.116
1 Linear Feet in two manuscript boxes.
The Medical Society of the County of Kings collection spans the period 1852 to 1981 and contains publications and ephemera pertaining to the Society, its library, and its affiliated medical centers, Brooklyn Eastern District Dispensary and Hospital and Williamsburgh Dispensary and Hospital.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Source and date of acquisition unknown. Formally accessioned in 1985.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by institution and chronologically.
Historical Note
The Medical Society of the County of Kings was founded in 1822, though the impetus for its founding had occurred in 1806, when the New York State Legislature, alarmed by increasing numbers of individuals falsely passing themselves off as medical professionals, passed "An Act to Incorporate Medical Societies for the Purpose of Regulating Physic and Surgery in this State." In accordance with the Act, each county in New York was to incorporate its own medical society comprised of its resident practicing physicians, and each medical society was to have a Board of Censors that examined and licensed medical practioners. The Medical Society of the County of Kings met at various locations in Brooklyn throughout most of the 19th century, until its first official building was constructed at 356 Bridge Street in 1887. A larger second building was opened in 1900 at 1313 Bedford Avenue.
Throughout the 19th century, the Society played a distinguished role in the development of the medical profession. In the first two decades after its founding, the Society concerned itself solely with the regulation of medical practice, but in the 1840s it also began to hold scientific meetings in which medical professionals could exchange information. Papers and case reports presented at these meetings were published in the New York Journal of Medicine. The Society also published its medical transactions in pamphlet form for distribution among its members, and these pamphlets later evolved into the monthly periodical The Proceedings, which was the predecessor of the distinguished Brooklyn Medical Journal, established in 1888. The Society also operated a highly regarded medical library, which was established in 1844 and grew to become the fifth largest medical library in the United States.
In 1870, the Society began establishing specialized sections, with the Brooklyn Pathological Society being the first. Several more were to follow in the ensuing decades. In the 1920s, the Society took on an educational role as well, providing graduate extension courses at the Long Island College of Medicine and holding highly attended lecture series at its building on Bedford Avenue. In 1933, the Society's name was legally changed to the Medical Society of the County of Kings and Academy of Medicine of Brooklyn to reflect its dual professional and educational roles, and it remained a vital resource for Brooklyn physicians throughout the rest of the 20th century. As of 2023, the Society continues to function as a regulating organization for Brooklyn medical professionals, examining and defending the credentials of its member physicans and encouraging the dissemination of accurate medical knowledge. The Society is now based in the Brooklyn neighborhood of Bay Ridge.
Sources:
Markowitz, Martin, ed. The Sesquicentennial Journal; Medical Society of the County of Kings, 1822-1972. Brooklyn, N.Y.: Medical Society of County of Kings, 1972.
Medical Society of the County of Kings, Inc. "About Our Society." Accessed November 17, 2010. http://www.msck.org/msck-practice.htm
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Norwegian Lutheran Deaconesses' Home and Hospital annual reports and receipts (ARC.246)
Brooklyn pharmacy and medicine bottles (2013.022)
Long Island College Hospital collection (ARC.139)
Jarvis S. Wight medical scrapbook (ARC.256)
Brooklyn ephemera collection (BCMS.0007)
Records of the Brooklyn Council for Social Planning (BCMS.0039)
Brooklyn hospitals and health services organizations collection (ARC.141)
Scope and Contents
The Medical Society of the County of Kings collection spans the period 1852 to 1981 and contains publications and ephemera pertaining to the Society, its library, and its allied medical centers. Items include annual reports, statutes and manuals, transactions and proceedings, newsletters, brochures, pamphlets, and programs.
Annual reports span 1852 to 1940. Only one report for the year 1927 pertains directly to the Society; the remaining reports concern the Society's library and allied medical centers, including the Brooklyn Eastern District Dispensary and the Williamsburgh Hospital and Dispensary. The reports are supplemented with by-laws, as well as information pertaining to staffing and standing committees, membership, financial expenditures, contributions and donations, medical cases and disease occurrences, and surgical procedures.
Statutes and manuals date from 1858 to 1888 and contain information on the regulation of medical practice as enacted by New York State, as well as the bylaws and code of ethics of the Medical Society of the County of Kings. Additional information includes listings of the Society's members, presidents, and officers.
The Society's transactions and proceedings are contained in publications spanning the period 1858 to 1877, some of which are issues of the Society's monthly periodical, The Proceedings. Contained within are the text of papers presented at the Society's meetings, various member physicians' reports on medical cases to which they have attended, and information on treatments and surgical procedures. Issues of The Proceedings also contain advertisements for various medical treatments.
Newsletters are comprised of the Society's monthly bulletin for the years 1935 and 1936, as well as one issue from 1981. Additional ephemera constitutes a small number of items, including a circa 1955 booklet containing a brief history of the Society, brochures and programs containing updates on the general activities of the Society and its library for the period circa 1900 to 1924, and a souvenir program for the annual music and dance event at the Williamsburgh Hospital for the year 1909.
Diseases |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medical ethics |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medical laws and legislation |z New York (State); Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Publications; Proceedings; Newsletters; Printed ephemera; Medicine |x Practice |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Physicians |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medicine |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Societies, etc.; Medicine |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Membership lists; Hospitals |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medical libraries |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Medical care |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Certificates of incorporation; Financial records; Annual reports; Statutes; Bylaws (administrative records); Medical Society of the County of Kings (Kings County, N.Y.). Library; Medical Society of the County of Kings and Academy of Medicine of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Eastern District Dispensary and Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Medical Society of the County of Kings (Kings County, N.Y.); Medical Society of the County of Kings and Academy of Medicine of Brooklyn (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.). Library; Williamsburgh Hospital (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Williamsburgh Dispensary (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Statues, By-Laws and Ethics, 1858 (Box 1)
- Transactions, 1858-1865 (Box 1)
- Member list, circa 1867 (Box 1)
- Manual, 1867, 1872, 1880, 1888 (Box 1)
- Proceedings, Vols. 1 and 2, 1876-1877 (Box 1)
- Meeting programs, 1921, 1924 (Box 1)
- Annual report, 1927 (Box 1)
- Kings County Trust Company booklet, circa 1955 (Box 1)
- Bulletin, 1924, 1935-1936, 1981 (Box 2)
- Report of Library Committee, 1867 (Box 2)
- Library pamphlet, circa 1900 (Box 2)
- Library Announcements, 1918, 1924 (Box 2)
- Library annual reports, 1923-1940 (Box 2)
- Brooklyn Eastern District Dispensary and Hospital annual reports, 1875, 1891, 1892 (Box 2)
- Williamsburgh Dispensary annual reports, 1852-1863, 1908 (Box 2)
- Williamsburgh Dispensary By-Laws, 1862 (Box 2)
- Williamsburgh Hospital annual report, 1908 (Box 2)
- Williamsburgh Hospital annual musicale and dance program, 1909 (Box 2)